The next set of solutions
really deal with improving
the quality and timing of your sleep.
Getting started right out the gates,
the most important thing you can do
to improve your sleep quality
is treating your sleep disorder
if you actually have one.
There are a number of
really easy solutions
depending upon what your
sleep problem actually is.
Think about this from the
perspective of a football player,
they're probably more likely
to be dealing with things like sleep apnea
because they're larger,
relative to say maybe a swimmer
whose issue is more likely
to be dealing with circadian rhythms
because they're oftentimes practicing
and training early in the morning.
So right out the gates,
just thinking about what
we're asking our bodies to do
gives us some strategies
for what type of disorder
we may likely have,
and then of course then
the solution for that.
In order to make my solutions
a little bit more straightforward,
what I want to do is talk
about getting to sleep faster
and then staying asleep more effectively.
So what are the reasons
why people struggle to fall asleep
and how can we improve that?
It can be a number of different things,
the obvious ones, but still important:
are we using stimulants
or caffeine too late
for our own physiology?
Some folks can metabolize
caffeine very quickly
and it doesn't affect them,
others really struggle if it's within,
you know, eight or more hours of sleep.
It can affect their overall sleep quality.
That's a common one.
Working or doing any
other stimulating events
at night can be a problem.
Where people really miss this
is the best way to probably
think about it is novelty.
So it's not the fact
that you're on your phone
or the fact that you're
watching TV or anything,
it's seeking of novelty.
That seems to be the big problem.
So it's okay for some folks,
I will be candid with you,
I watch a little bit of TV
basically every night before sleep.
But what you don't want to do are things
that cause you to seek novelty
and so your phone becomes problematic
because something new will pop up
and it'll reward that pattern
of seeing something new and
novel and get you excited.
And so what you don't want to do
is watch TV shows that are that,
you don't want to watch things
that are aggravating,
or arousing or exciting.
You want to watch, typically,
things that are more interesting
but not overly stimulating.
This is "Planet Earth."
This is not murder mysteries,
this is not things that get you aggravated
and irritated like the news
and political events and things like that.
And so that is what you
want to be cautious of.
Eating too close to bed can be a problem.
However, however, and this is
important, people miss this.
There's excellent research
showing small snacks before bed
can enhance sleep quality
and reduce sleep latency.
Specifically, kiwis are well studied
as effective sleep aids.
Higher glycemic index
meals pretty close to bed,
again, low amounts can be great.
We certainly don't want
to eat high amounts
and increased digestion or heart rate
and problems like that,
but small snacks for some people
can actually be really effective
at putting you to sleep.
Probably most important
to all this, though,
is really the pattern
and if you look around at
any of the sleep research
or talk to sleep experts,
they're going to talk about the need
to make sure that your
sleeping environment
is really a sleep sanctuary.
Our body has probably one tool
better than anything else,
and that's the ability
to pattern recognize
and this becomes a problem.
If you go into sleep environments
and you are anticipating
a pattern of sleep issues,
then that pattern is going to persist.
If you have the opposite,
then that pattern will persist.
And so what we see a lot of times,
our solution strategies
for people having a
hard time going to sleep
despite the fact that they're doing
all these other things right,
and this is common, right?
Oh, I don't have caffeine.
I stop working, you
know, many hours before.
I don't eat before, I meditate before,
I do breath work, I do all these things
and then I still struggle with sleep.
Okay, great.
I'm not watching TV,
all those other things.
Why am I still struggling to fall asleep?
Well, oftentimes it's the fact
that you think about
struggling to fall asleep
that's causing that pattern to persist.
So how do we solve that?
We take clocks away.
You don't get to measure
and you don't get to see your sleep score.
You don't get to see your
sleep latency number,
you don't get to look at the clock
and think about how long it's
taking you to fall asleep.
So all of those are also tools
to take that out of the equation
and reframe the approach into thinking,
"When I get into bed,
this is an awesome opportunity to sleep,"
rather than, "Oh my gosh,
I'm going to get into bed
and have another night
where I can't fall asleep."
That's a bad framework to be in
and you want to get out of that
as quickly as you possibly can.
These environmental
pattern recognition things
are so strong, you can actually
use it to your advantage;
especially when traveling.
Everyone knows of the first night effect,
which is when you are
in a new destination,
you struggle to sleep the first night
but tend to sleep a lot better the second
or third and subsequent nights.
Well a lot of that is because
you're in a different environment, right?
We aren't seeing and smelling and hearing
the same things we did in our house.
So if we can artificially
create that in our house
and take that on the road,
we can dramatically
improve our sleep quality
and specifically our sleep onset.
Think about smell as the easiest one.
If you take a scent that you like,
common ones are lavender,
and you put a little lavender
on your bed at night in
your house every night,
you stand to associate
that smell with safe,
secure, high quality sleep, et cetera.
You take that on the road with you, then,
put that on your new mattress
or bed or wherever you go.
Those same sense will kick in,
the same pattern recognition will happen,
and ideally you'll have
the same quality of sleep.
You can do a similar thing
with temperature, right?
If you have a set temperature of your bed,
you may not be able to take
that entire cooling mattress
with you on the road,
but there are things like cooling pillows.
So you use that same temperature
on your pillow at home,
take that pillow or pillowcase with you,
and now you have a mimicked environment.
You can combine a couple of
different things like that
and you should really
improve your sleep latency
when you're on the road.
Now when it comes to
staying asleep at night,
there's a bunch of different
solutions we can talk about.
One of my most common ones is hydration.
If you drink too much water,
of course you're going to
wake up and have to urinate
and that's going to cause
you to get up a whole bunch.
But really, some folks don't understand
that sleep quality will
be a big determinant
upon how frequently you get up to go pee.
If you are waking up more
than once and you go to pee,
there's a large volume there, it is clear
and that's happening
the next morning as well
when you wake up and you
still have a lot of pee,
then you probably have an issue
of drinking too much pure water.
In that case, just
reduce your water intake
for a couple of hours prior to bed
and you should be fine.
Funny enough, we've had plenty
of our high performing clients,
our high performing executives
in our coaching programs
come to us with all kinds of problems
with their physiology and
performance and brain fog,
and really all of it
boiled down to the fact
that they drank way too
much water at night.
It was tanking their sleep.
We moved that and within days,
they're sleeping for ten hours
for the first time in 15 years.
I have so many examples of that
where it's pretty silly, honestly,
where I'm like man, you
spent a lot of money and time
to figure out you drink way
too much water at night.
So, it can be quite that simple.
Other times, though, it's
a little bit deceiving;
so folks will oftentimes
think that's the problem.
If it's not the case,
you're waking up and there's
not a lot of volume there
or there is like one time
and then the second time it's a lot less
or it's you know, more yellow colored,
or in the morning you wake up
and realize you didn't even pee
for 45 minutes after waking up,
this is sometimes an
issue of sleep quality.
And so what happens is typically at night,
you're supposed to be sending
signals to your kidneys
that says hey, stop filtering
and producing urine.
And so obviously we don't want
to be waking up to do that
all throughout the night.
If you're of a low quality sleep though,
for any number of reasons,
that signal can continue to be sent
and so you can continue to make the urine.
And so people think
that their sleep quality
is being ruined by the fact
that they have to get up and pee,
when the honest reality is they're peeing
because they're already basically awake.
And so that is another way to figure out,
hmm, maybe I have a disorder,
maybe I should get checked out,
maybe something is going on
'cause I'm waking up to pee a lot
and really there's not a lot there;
I probably should get checked out.
Another really common
one is sleep position.
We see this routinely where
80 plus percentages of
people's sleep problems
happen when they're on one
position of their body.
Most commonly it's your back.
And so avoiding sleeping
directly on your back
and sleeping either on your sides,
as a blanket rule though
not true for everyone,
can really dramatically
improve people's sleep.
I've told this story earlier
of one of my professional athletes
I've worked with having this issue,
but we have seen this time and time again.
And so getting some assessment or analysis
of what's happening in
your sleep position,
this is a similar story to ergonomics.
So making sure that your bed and mattress
and pillow are all comfortable
can also be really important factors
to your overall sleep quality.
Outside of that, we start now talking
about environmental factors.
You probably have heard ad nauseam
about of course temperature.
You want to be comfortable there
and we want to be probably
a little bit cooler
than we are during the day,
but even noise.
We want to be less than 35 decibels.
Anything above that
tends to create problems.
This is where actually
things like pink noise
start to come into play.
There's a lot of really interesting
research coming out on that.
It's a little bit deeper than white noise
and it's not really publicly
available for the most part,
but the research thus
far is quite impressive.
The issue with white
noise or sleep machines
is the fact that above 35 decibels,
they can actually create sleep problems
because they're so loud.
And so while it's great
to kind of drown out the
background information,
you don't want to be in a position
where you're actually too loud.
Depending on where you live,
if you're especially
in an urban environment
and you have lots of external
sound stuff going on,
you may want to actually turn to
something like earplugs
instead of a sleep
machine for that purpose.
Though, earplugs may create problems
with ear pain and discomfort
and stuff like that.
So again, choose the best tool
that you have for your situation.
But really, below 35 decibels
is the gold standard there.
Again, ideally in the show notes here,
we've got the link to my paper
that you can go through all 11 factors,
but other ones that are
really common are CO2.
There's emerging evidence
that when that thing gets
above 900 parts per million
and then really specifically
in exaggerated scenarios
of above like 2,400 parts per million,
that this can dramatically
impact sleep quality,
sleep onset and sleep latency;
as well as next day wakefulness,
memory and decision making,
and a bunch of other
cognitive performance tasks.
So many, many other factors
that go into your sleep quality
such as your environment,
that will have in the show notes.
Last thing I want to talk
about here is snoring.
Now I don't want to overly concern you,
everybody snores at some point or another.
It doesn't necessarily mean,
it probably doesn't mean
you have a sleep disorder,
though it's not totally benign
if you're a chronic or excessive snorer;
that's really the problem here.
It's not a normal function.
It's common, but it's not normal.
Now one thing that's actually quite funny
that we laugh about on my team a lot,
is how frequently people
come into our programs
because of sleep issues,
and they've tried everything.
They've done all the
stuff we've talked about,
they've had sleep studies done before,
and they came back either
like really moderate
or nothing at all
and they maybe think
their testosterone is low
or maybe it is;
and they've run through everything,
like I just cannot sleep.
And we do one little test on him
and realize, wow, has your
sleep partner been assessed?
Like, oh my sleep partner
just snores like crazy.
And we always chuckle 'cause I'm like man,
I got really bad news for you.
Your sleep is fine,
but your partner's sleep
is a complete disaster
and they're ruining your sleep.
So we've had a lot of
people come into our program
and then basically switch.
So the person that paid initially said,
don't even do me anymore,
do this on my sleep partner,
on my husband or my wife, whatever.
Fix their sleep.
And then that original
person's sleep disorder
quote-unquote goes away
immediately and permanently.
And this has happened,
like you can hear me literally laughing,
'cause it's happened so many times
and I don't feel bad about it
'cause the people sleep
perfectly afterwards
because we found the real problem
and it had nothing to do with them.
And so snoring can be a
real problem with sleep.
And so really making
sure that it's not you,
it's not your sleeping partner,
or a lot of the cases it's their dog.
Not often cats are snoring that loud,
but dogs that's really, really common.
And so that that can be really disruptive
to overall sleep.
If it is you personally,
we'll go back to that example.
You can try just going with
something like mouth tape.
I've done that a ton, I use it a ton,
especially using a
combination of nasal dilators;
so either nasal strips
or something like that
to open up your nasal passageways
as well as mouth tape.
And I will be candid with you,
we've had a lot of success with that.
And sometimes that step alone
really can improve snoring
and solve a lot of sleep problems.
It doesn't always happen, though.
So if it doesn't, then
you probably need to go
to the next step one way or the other.
But it can absolutely be a viable solution
and is a nice place to start.
And just to be really clear,
the next step I'm talking about
is usually getting a sleep study done,
but you can try other stuff as well.
We've already talked about,
position is another common solution.
Generally people don't
snore on their sides
and if they do, not
nearly as much or as loud
as they are when they're on their back.
So just try investing in
one of those sleep pillows
I talked about earlier
that forces you to sleep
on your left or right side.
Sometimes that solves
the problem immediately.
There are also tongue
exercises you can do.
We can actually have
a whole protocol here in the show notes.
This is very free, it's
going to take typically
four to eight weeks to have
some sort of an effect,
but there is strong research
behind tongue strengthening exercises
to resolve that problem.
Sometimes there is no solution,
it is anatomical and
you either have to have
some sort of nasal surgery
or put in some sort of a
mouthpiece to resolve that problem,
and then sometimes not even that works.
But for the most part,
something in that solution
that I just went over
is going to either dramatically help,
if not completely solve
your snoring problems.
If you enjoyed this clip,
you can watch the full
episode by clicking here.
[music]